ok so for today's problem we've got this
compound here with a carbonyl and a
methyl group and our target molecule has
a methyl and a bromo group and what we
want to be able to do is figure out how
to get from here to here in two steps, give it a shot.
as we're analyzing this, let's take a look at the molecule
we're realizing that we have to lose oxygen, we
have to figure out a way to get that
oxygen atom off of there, and we also have to
figure out a way to get a bromine atom
on there, and so we have two steps to
play with, either one is gonna get rid of
the oxygen one is gonna add the bromine
or somehow both can happen at once but
what we definitely want to do is get rid of
that oxygen, so we don't really know of a
way to remove a carbonyl oxygen so why
don't we reduce it. let's take sodium
borohydride, just a nice soft reducing
agent, and let's as step 1 reduce the
carbonyl. we're gonna get an alcohol. now
that we have an alcohol we have some
different possibilities to think about.
now one possibility that we might wanna
use is some strong acid to
protonate that hydroxyl group, get it
to leave as a water molecule, but then what we want to
do is choose a strong acid selectively that
might perform the other transformation
that we also want to occur, so why don't we
use hydrobromic acid and see what happens.
so once again the first step was that
we had some hydride and that went ahead
and reduced it so here is our alcohol,
now if we use hydrobromic acid
we're gonna get that right there, so the
hydroxyl has been protonated, now water
is a good leaving group, we are in acidic
conditions, so carbocations are going to be
fine, so that can go ahead and leave. now
the interesting thing here is if we have
a secondary carbocation, and remember
that a secondary carbocation that is
adjacent to a tertiary or quaternary
carbon, you're probably gonna get some
kind of hydride or or methanide shift.
and so what's happening here is we've
got this implied hydrogen and what we
can do is it'll spontaneously just do a
hydride shift and so if this hydride
moves over there that's going to
neutralize that carbocation, it's gonna leave a
carbocation at the tertiary position. once
again this happens because the tertiary carbocation is
more stable than a secondary carbocation, so that
is going to happen spontaneously and
pretty much instantly. and now since we
used hydrobromic acid, when this
deprotonated, its gonna leave a lot of
bromide swimming around in solution and
so that's going to kill two birds with
one stone because if there's a lot of
bromide and one finds this carbocation
it is absolutely going to react and
generate the intended product. so because
we were clever in the selection of acid,
we've been able to induce this in two steps.
the first thing we did was reduce that
ketone to the alcohol and then because
we used HBr we are able to get that
water to leave, allow this carbocation
rearrangement to occur spontaneously and
then the free bromide ion swimming
around in solution finds the carbocation and there we go, we get our product
thanks for watching guys, subscribe to my
channel for more tutorials and as always
feel free to email me